Finding Aid for Robert F. Williams papers, 1948-2014
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Robert F. Williams papers 1948-2014
Williams, Robert F., 1925-1996
85506 Aa 2, UAl
African American civil rights activist and black militant leader in Monroe County North Carolina who came to advocate armed self-defense in response to violence, left the United States in 1961 and lived in Cuba and China until 1969 when he settled in Baldwin Michigan. Papers include correspondence, newspaper clippings, audio-visual material, manuscripts, petitions, and government documents documenting the civil rights movement, black nationalism, radical politics in the United States and Williams's experiences in Cuba and China.
14.5 linear feet
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The bulk of the collection was donated by Robert F. Williams beginning in 1976. Periodic additions have been received. Donor no. 5869. In 2011, his son John C. Williams (donor no. 10647) donated additional materials.
The collection is open for research.
A microfilm edition of the Robert F. Williams papers has been produced University Publications of America as part of its Black Studies Research Sources series. The microfilm includes the entirety of the Bentley Historical Library's Robert F. Williams collection (except the motion picture and audio and video recordings). A guide to the microfilm edition is available in pdf format at http://www.lexisnexis.com/documents/academic/upa_cis/9353_BlackPowerMovemPt2.pdf
Robert Franklin Williams was at various times in his life a civil rights leader, a black militant, an author and resident of Cuba and later the People's Republic of China. Although he was not recognized as one of the major black militants during the civil rights upheavals of the 1960s, he was one of the earliest and most important black militant leaders. Born in 1925, Williams grew up in Monroe, Union County, North Carolina. He was trained as a machinist in the National Youth Administration, and later attended West Virginia State College and Johnson C. Smith University. Following a tour of duty in the Marine Corps, Williams returned to Monroe in 1955. In the same year he was elected president of the local chapter of the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP), and began a career in the struggle for civil rights that would eventually lead him to exile in Cuba and the People's Republic of China.
As president of the Union County NAACP, Williams not only revitalized the organization, but also began a non-violent campaign to integrate the county's public facilities. The attempts to integrate the public facilities, such as the swimming pool, were largely unsuccessful and often were met by violent resistance. Repudiating the NAACP policy of passive non-resistance, Williams began to advocate a stronger means of defense by blacks. He urged that blacks arm themselves and meet violence with violence. Williams' stand on this question eventually forced a minor split in the NAACP because many black leaders had become increasingly impatient with passive non-resistance. Williams was temporarily suspended from the NAACP, but many blacks in Union County heeded his advice and did arm themselves.
Racial violence in Monroe culminated in August 1961 when Freedom Riders arrived in the county to call national attention to the situation in Monroe. On August 26th violence exploded. Williams and other blacks fought back with guns. During the height of the violence, a car containing a white couple inadvertently wandered into the black neighborhood. Williams gave the couple refuge in his home, but was charged with kidnapping and a warrant was issued for his arrest by county officials. Rather than risking arrest in this racially torn community, Williams fled to New York City. Now faced with interstate flight from a warrant, Williams' crime became a federal crime and the FBI entered the case. Williams then fled to Canada and later to Cuba where Premier Fidel Castro offered him political asylum. Williams' interpretation of this affair can be found in his book Negroes with Guns.
In Cuba Williams' black militancy hardened. He became one of the most outspoken critics of the United States and called upon blacks to arm themselves for the battle ahead. To communicate his ideas, Williams began to publish The Crusader, a black militant journal, and also began to broadcast a program called "Radio Free Dixie". The radicalization of Williams' ideology and the changing attitudes of blacks in the United States can be traced through Williams' correspondence. Further evidence can also be found in the collection of The Crusader and "Radio Free Dixie" transcripts. He also wrote several articles in various radical journals.
After five years in Cuba, Williams became disenchanted with Castro's views of the black in America. For this reason, he left Cuba and traveled to the People's Republic of China where he established a new residency. As a friend of Mao Tse Tung and Chou En Lai, Williams redoubled his criticism of the treatment of blacks in America. About this time in 1966, Williams moved toward black separatism. He was elected president of the Detroit-based Republic for New Africa. The leaders of the Republic called for a separate state for blacks within the United States. Williams had reached the full development of his ideology: from a proponent of passive resistance as a NAACP leader, to a black militant, to a black self-determinist. The folder on the Republic of New Africa in the collection clearly illustrates his self-determinist ideology.
In 1969, Williams decided to end his self-imposed exile and return to the United States. Upon return, he settled in Baldwin, Michigan. In 1970-71 he served as a research associate in the Center for Chinese Studies at the University of Michigan. Drawing from his extensive stay in China, Williams advised political scientist Allen Whiting who in turn advised Henry Kissinger shortly before Kissinger's first trip to China. The last major battle of Williams' career came in 1975 when the state of North Carolina requested that he be brought back to face the 1961 kidnapping charges. Despite a large campaign to stop Williams' extradition, Governor William Milliken of Michigan extradited him. Following his acquittal, Williams returned to Baldwin. In the 1980s and 1990s, Williams remained active in community affairs in Baldwin and took up the cause of Clyde Cleveland, a prisoner on death row in North Carolina. Williams died in 1996.
The collection is divided into two subgroups based on the dates of accessioning: 1976-1979 and 1983-1997.
The Robert Williams papers, dating from 1951, include correspondence, notes, newspaper clippings, audio-visual material, manuscripts, petitions, and government documents. The collection documents a wide variety of subjects: the American civil rights movement, Black Nationalism, cold war politics, Castro’s Cuba, Mao’s China, and the radical left in the United States.
As Robert Williams continued to add to his collection following his initial donation in 1976, it was necessary to arrange and describe the materials based on groupings of dates of accessioning. Thus the bulk of the collection is divided into two subgroups: 1976-1979 Accessions and 1983-1997 Accessions with much overlapping of material. In addition, the collection contains a small series of papers collected by his son John C. Williams and a separate series of Audio-Visual Materials.
Subjects:
Williams, Robert F. (Robert Franklin), 1925-1996.; Republic of New Afrika.; China--History--1949-1976.; Cuba.; Detroit (Mich.); Lake County (Mich.); African Americans.; Afro-Americans--Michigan.; Civil rights--United States.
Subject - Visual materials:
Williams, Robert F. (Robert Franklin), 1925-1996.; Africa.; Vietnam.; African Americans.
Genre/Form:
Motion pictures.; Videotapes.; Photographs.
- 1976-1979 Accessions
  The first subgroup (1976-1979 Accessions) is divided into seven series: Correspondence, Manuscripts and Writings, Public Statements and Publicity, Biographical Material, The Republic of New Africa, The Crusader, and “Radio Free Dixie” Transcripts.
  - Correspondence
    The Correspondence series (1956-1979) consists primarily of incoming personal, political and legal correspondence. Topics covered range from international political theory to Williams legal status. Correspondents include attorney Conrad Lynn, various political compatriots, academics, students, and members of the press.
    - Undated, 5 folders (Box 1)
    - 1956 (Box 1)
    - 1959-1967, 34 folders (Box 1)
    - 1968-1979, 37 folders (Box 2)
  - Manuscripts and Writings
    The Manuscripts and Writings series (1961-1970) consists primarily of article and book manuscripts, and includes some published articles by, and interviews with, Williams. The series also contains several books authored or co-authored by Williams.
    - Undated, 5 folders (Box 2)
    - 1961-1962 (Box 2)
    - 1963-1964 (Box 2)
    - 1965-1967 (Box 2)
    - Manuscript article entitled "From Peking, I Speak Again" (Box 2)
      (Addition to Negroes with Guns)
    - Manuscript article entitled "The World Black Revolution" (Box 2)
    - Manuscript article entitled "Listen Brother!" (Box 2)
      (a monologue)
    - Miscellaneous notes and other writings (Box 2)
    - Published articles by Williams (Box 2)
      (newspaper, periodicals, and poetry)
    - Book: Negroes with Guns, by Robert Williams, 2 copies (Box 3)
    - Pamphlet: Black Vanguard, containing excerpt from Negroes with Guns 1965 (Box 3)
    - Book: La Revolution aux états-unis by James Boggs and Robert Williams (Box 3)
    - Book: International Conference for Solidarity with the People of Vietnam Against U.S. Imperialist Aggression and for the Defense of Peace (Box 3)
      (Includes speech by Robert Williams on the Revolutionary Action Movement)
  - Public Statements and Publicity
    The Public Statements and Publicity series (1956-1979) consists of Williams' press statements, speeches, letters sent to newspapers, and political flyers.
    - Letters to newspaper editors by Williams 1966-1984 (Box 3)
    - Speeches 1956-1968, undated, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Press releases 1961-1969, undated, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous statements, press releases, and other writings 1965-1970, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Political flyers 1964-1979, undated, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Biographical Material
    The Biographical Material series (1962-1979) includes material on the Monroe case, government testimony by Williams, legal papers, personal documents and articles about Williams.
    - Papers concerning Monroe, North Carolina "kidnapping" (Box 3)
    - Miscellany concerning Robert Williams, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Personal miscellany (travel visas, etc.) (Box 3)
    - Legal papers and government testimony 1966-1970, undated, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Articles about Williams in foreign-language newspapers, 7 folders (Box 3)
    - Itineraries (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous black publications, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous Cuban publications (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous Chinese and Asian materials, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Miscellany (Box 3)
    - Articles concerning Robert Williams 1957-1979, undated, 36 folders (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous newspaper and periodical articles, 5 folders (Box 4)
  - Republic of New Africa Material
    The Republic of New Africa (RNA) series (1968-1970) consists of two folders of papers related to the RNA.
    - Republic of New Africa papers 1968-1970, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - The Crusader (newsletter) [microfilm copy available]
    The Crusader series (1959-1963) consists of issues of Williams' newsletter, which covered personal and political matters.
    - 1959-1963, 1980, 9 folders (Box 5)
    - Subscription lists (Box 5)
  - "Radio Free Dixie" Broadcasts
    The "Radio Free Dixie" Transcripts series (1962-1966) consists of printed transcripts of Williams' radio broadcasts from Cuba.
    - 1962-1964, 15 folders (Box 5)
    - 1964-1966, 15 folders (Box 6)
    - "The Robert Williams Hour" (Box 6)
    - Undated, 1962 (Box 6)
- 1983-1997 Accessions
  The 1983-1997 Accessions subgroup is divided into ten series: Calvin Cunningham case, Clippings, Correspondence, Government documents, Lake County materials, Memorial materials, Personal material, Political Organizations, Press Releases and Publicity, and Print and Broadcast Material.
  - Calvin Cunningham Case
    The Calvin Cunningham case series (1983-1996) consists of material concerning Williams' advocacy on behalf of a death-row inmate, Calvin Cunningham. In 1991, Cunningham was convicted of murder in the 1990 shooting death of a policeman in Charlotte, North Carolina. Cunningham maintained his innocence.
    - 1983-1996, 5 folders (Box 7)
  - Clippings
    The Clippings series (1961-1996) consists of clippings from American and international newspapers and magazines concerning Robert Williams.
    - 1961-1984 (Box 7)
    - 1963-1966 (Box 7)
    - 1964-1966 Vietnam and China (Box 7)
    - 1968-1980 (Box 7)
    - 1968-1970 Chinese (Box 7)
    - 1969-1979 (Box 7)
    - 1969-1985 (Box 7)
    - 1970-1976 (Box 7)
    - 1970-1992 (Box 7)
    - 1975-1976 (Box 7)
    - 1976-1986 (Box 7)
    - 1980-1995 (Box 7)
    - 1983-1986 (Box 7)
    - 1993-1996 (Box 7)
    - Undated Libya (Box 7)
  - Correspondence
    The Correspondence series (1961-1996) covers personal and political issues. Correspondents include political allies, journalists, government officials, scholars, and friends.
    - 1962-1965, undated (Box 7)
    - Anne Olson 1961-1966 (Box 7)
    - 1961-1966 (Box 7)
    - 1961-1966 (Box 7)
      (in Chinese)
    - 1961-1966 (Box 7)
    - 1961-1966 (Box 7)
    - 1961-1966 and undated (Box 7)
    - 1976-1978, 3 folders (Box 7)
    - 1978-1996 (Box 7)
    - 1979-1980, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Regarding document declassification 1980-1983 (Box 7)
    - 1980-1983 (Box 7)
    - 1980-1983 (Box 7)
    - 1980-1996 (Box 7)
    - 1981 (Box 8)
    - 1982-1983 (Box 8)
    - 1984 (Box 8)
    - 1985 (Box 8)
    - 1986 (Box 8)
    - Michigan Civil Rights Commission re Lake County 1987 (Box 8)
    - Felon Flyers 1985-1990 (Box 8)
    - Desoto Productions 1982-1987 (Box 8)
    - Ora Mobley 1989-1992 (Box 8)
    - 1990 (Box 8)
    - 1990-1996, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - 1991 (Box 8)
    - 1992 (Box 8)
    - 1993-1995 (Box 8)
    - 1995-1996 (Box 8)
  - Government Files
    The Government Document series (1951-1981) consists of material Robert Williams received from government agencies through Freedom of Information Act requests. The series is subdivided into seven subseries based on the government agency which produced the documents: FBI, CIAIRS, Michigan State Police, Federal Post Office, State Department, and Treasury Department. In some cases, the provenance of the documents was unclear. For instance, unfoldered copies of documents produced by the Michigan State Police might have been gathered and released by the FBI or CIA. Where the identity of the agency that released documents was unclear, those documents were organized by the government agency which originally produced the document. The FBI subseries is subdivided into two sub-subseries based on their system of organization. Where possible, the original filing system used by the FBI (documents are organized into numbered sections) has been preserved, and where that system was disorganized or obscured, the documents were arranged in a rough chronological order.
    - FBI Documents
      - Organized by FBI Filing System
        - Section 1 1951-1960 (Box 8)
        - Section 2 1955-1961, 3 folders (Box 8)
        - Section 3 1961, 4 folders (Box 8)
        - Section 5 1961-1965, 4 folders (Box 8)
        - Section 6 1962-1965, 2 folders (Box 8)
        - Section 7 1963 (Box 8)
        - Section 8 1964-1969 (Box 8)
        - Section 8 1967 (Box 9)
        - Section 9 1968-1969 (Box 9)
        - Section 11 1968-1969, 2 folders (Box 9)
        - Section 12 1969 (Box 9)
        - Section 13 1969-1970 (Box 9)
        - Section 14 1970-1971 (Box 9)
        - Section 15 1961-1973 (Box 9)
        - Section 16 1971-1972, 2 folders (Box 9)
        - Section 17 1973-1974 (Box 9)
        - Section 18 1974-1976 (Box 9)
      - Chronological
        - 1952-1965 (Box 9)
        - 1952-1970 (Box 9)
        - 1955-1970 (Box 9)
        - FBI and Michigan State Police 1955-1972, 2 folders (Box 9)
        - 1955-1972, 2 folders (Box 9)
        - 1959-1968 (Box 9)
        - 1959-1973 (Box 9)
        - 1960-1961 (Box 9)
        - 1960-1975 (Box 9)
        - 1961, 2 folders (Box 9)
        - 1961, 2 folders (Box 10)
        - 1961-1969 (Box 10)
        - 1961-1971, 2 folders (Box 10)
        - 1961-1973, 2 folders (Box 10)
        - 1962-1966 (Box 10)
        - 1962-1975 (Box 10)
        - 1962-1976 (Box 10)
        - Radio Transcripts: "Radio Free Dixie" 1962-1968, 3 folders (Box 10)
        - 1963-1968 (Box 10)
        - 1963-1970 (Box 10)
        - 1963-1972 (Box 10)
        - 1963-1976, 2 folders (Box 10)
        - 1964-1966 (Box 10)
        - 1964-1968 (Box 10)
        - 1964-1970 (Box 10)
        - 1964-1973 (Box 10)
        - 1964-1973 (Box 10)
        - 1965-1966 (Box 10)
        - 1965-1970 (Box 10)
        - 1966-1971 (Box 10)
        - 1967 (Box 10)
        - 1967-1968 (Box 10)
        - 1967-1970 (Box 10)
        - 1968 (Box 10)
        - 1968-1969, 2 folders (Box 10)
        - 1968-1970 (Box 10)
        - 1968-1971 (Box 10)
        - 1968-1972 (Box 10)
        - 1968-1973 (Box 10)
        - 1968-1975 (Box 10)
        - 1969, 3 folders (Box 11)
        - 1969-1970, 2 folders (Box 11)
        - 1969-1971, 2 folders (Box 11)
        - 1969-1972 (Box 11)
        - 1969-1973, 2 folders (Box 11)
        - 1970-1972 (Box 11)
        - 1971 (Box 11)
    - CIA Documents
      - 1961-1968 (Box 11)
      - 1962-1968 (Box 11)
    - IRS Documents
      - 1962-1972 (Box 11)
      - 1969-1981 (Box 11)
      - 1972-1973 (Box 11)
    - Michigan State Police Documents
      - 1968-1971 (Box 11)
      - 1969 (Box 11)
    - Post Office Documents
      - 1967-1968 (Box 11)
    - State Department Documents
      - 1960-1973 (Box 11)
      - 1961-1971 (Box 11)
      - 1961-1973 (Box 11)
        (Includes account of State Department interview with Williams re China)
      - 1967-1972 (Box 11)
      - 1968-1969 (Box 11)
      - 1968-1980 (Box 11)
        (Includes Williams correspondence with State and Justice Departments re Freedom of Information Act requests)
    - Treasury Department Files
      - 1976-1981 (Box 11)
  - Lake County
    The Lake County series (1977-1994) consists of correspondence, clippings and reports regarding Williams community activism in Lake County, Michigan.
    - Conflict between community and police 1977-1993 (Box 11)
    - Empowerment Zone 1994 (Box 11)
  - Memorial
    The Memorial series (1996) consists of obituaries, memorials and letters of condolence regarding Williams' death.
    - Obituaries and memorials 1996 (Box 11)
    - Letters of condolence 1996 (Box 11)
    - Memorial clippings 1996, 2 folders (Box 11)
  - Personal
    The Personal series (1961-1996) consists of personal and biographical material documenting Williams' life. The series is subdivided into four subseries: biographical manuscripts written about Williams, financial and legal documents, miscellaneous clippings and biographical material, and Williams personal writings.
    - Biographical
      - Draft of M. Ron Karenga Book 1979 (Box 11)
      - Tim Tyson Manuscript undated (Box 11)
    - Documents
      - Financial Statements 1961-1969 (Box 12)
      - Contracts and agreements 1961-1986 (Box 12)
      - University of Michigan Fellowship 1970-1973 (Box 12)
    - Miscellaneous Material
      - Miscellaneous Personal Documents and Biographical material 1978-1996 (Box 12)
      - 1960-1997 (Box 12)
      - 1965-1983 (Box 12)
      - Notes, correspondence, clippings 1969-1975 (Box 12)
      - 1981-1990 (Box 12)
      - 1995-1996 (Box 12)
    - Writings
      - Poetry 1983-1986 (Box 12)
      - Miscellaneous 1997 (Box 12)
      - Memoir Manuscript undated (Box 12)
  - Political Organizations
    The Political Organizations series consists of Williams' correspondence and printed material about three political organizations: the African-Descendant National Independence Partition Party, Committee to Aid Monroe Defendants, and the Sparticist League.
    - African-Descendant Nationalist Independence Partition (AD NIP) Party 1960-66 (Box 12)
    - Committee to Aid Monroe Defendants 1962-1975 (Box 12)
    - Sparticist League 1978-1984 (Box 12)
  - Press Releases and Publicity
    The Press Releases and Publicity series (1963-1985) includes letters to editors, press releases, speeches, and speaking engagement publicity.
    - Press relations 1963-1985 (Box 12)
    - Speaking engagement announcements 1972-1984, 2 folders (Box 12)
    - Press releases, speeches and notes 1979-1983, undated (Box 12)
    - Speeches and press releases undated (Box 12)
  - Print and Broadcast Material
    The Print and Broadcast Material series (1965-1991) includes copies of The Crusader, transcripts of "Radio Free Dixie" and a radio transcript from 1991.
    - The Crusader 1980 (Box 12)
    - Radio Free Dixie transcript 1965, undated (Box 12)
    - "Like It Is" radio transcript 1991 (Box 12)
- 2011 accession (John C. Williams, collector)
  The John C. Williams collection of Robert F. and Mabel Williams materials includes a scattering of papers from the period following Williams’ passing in 1996 and well as some letters, published material, and subject files covering the 1970s through the 1990s.
  - Robert L. and Mabel Williams papers
    - Calvin Cunningham letters and legal documents (Box 12)
    - Assorted cards (birthday, get-well, sympathy, etc. (Box 12)
    - China miscellaneous, cards, letters, programs, etc. 1990s (Box 12)
      (include material accumulated from trip to China for the 50th anniversary celebration of the People's Republic of China)
    - Hsinhua News Agency News Bulletin 1977 (Box 12)
    - Chinese newspapers 1977 (Box 12)
    - Various litigation and complaints (Box 12)
    - Mabel Williams: Appreciation Day 1996 and other Lake County and Baldwin, Michigan activities (Box 12)
    - Photographs, 1970 trip to Boston; youth demonstration; family snapshots (Box 12)
    - Vicki Garvin: letter to Mabel and "Tribute to Robert Williams" 1996 (Box 12)
    - John Herman Williams brochure 1999 (Box 12)
    - Publications containing references to Robert Williams (Box 12)
    - Robert F. Williams Community and Family Service Center 2000 (Box 12)
    - Robert F. Williams testimonials: from Detroit City Council November 1, 1996 and from Wesley Steele (Box 12)
    - Robert F. Williams -- scattered letters (Box 12)
- Audio-Visual
  The Audio Visual series (1964-1996) consists of three subseries: sound recordings, photographs, and videocassettes. The sound recordings include audio tape reels of Williams' "Radio Free Dixie" broadcasts, an oral history on cassette tape, a recording of a public discussion on China in which Williams participated, and a radio interview with Williams. The photograph subseries richly document Williams' residences in Cuba, China, and the United States.
  - Sound Recordings, compact discs except where indicated
    (original reel-to-reel tapes and CD master copies and duplicating copies have been removed to box 15)
    - Radio Free Dixie broadcasts
      - November 1964, Hanoi, Vietnam Conference-- Speeches of Anna Louise Strong and RFW Undated, 1 audiocassettes; 1 optical disks CD-Rs (Box 13)
      - December 11, 1964 Sidney Brecht (Blues); Max Roach -- Ray Charles -- Gravy Train Waltz, 1 audiocassettes; 2 optical disks CD-Rs (Box 13)
      - Undated Ordeal of Change reading, 1 audiocassettes; 1 optical disks CD-Rs (Box 13)